Fatih SAYIN

Austin, TX 78729 | fmsayin@hotmail.com| (512) 765 3221 | https://www.linkedin.com/in/fatih-sayin

GitHub: https://github.com/fmsayin | Portfolio: https://fmsayin.github.io

CAREER SUMMARY

A strategic, multidisciplinary data analyst with an eye for innovation and analytical perspective. Five year of previous expertise on research and data analytics combined with the best creative data visualizations, actionable insights, and approximation algorithms available. Experience with the tools such as VBA, Python, Ipython, Pandas, SQL, MongoDB, JavaScript, Tableau, Scikit-Learn, and PySpark.

EDUCATION

The University of Texas at Austin | Data Analytics and Visualization | 2019 Ivane Javakhishvili State University | Georgia | Ph.D. | 2009

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Data and Quantitative Analysis
- Decision Analytics
- Machine Learning, Predictive Modeling
- Data-Driven Personalization
- Big Data Queries and Interpretation
- Data Mining and Visualization Tools
- Tableau

- Advanced Excel Functions: Pivot Tables, VBA Scripting
- Fundamental Statistics: Modeling, Forecasting
- Programming: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib,
- API Interactions, Social Media Mining
- Databases: SQL, MongoDB
- Research, Reports, and Forecasts
- Web Visualization: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Dashboarding, JavaScript, Leaflet

MOST RECENT PROJECTS & ACCOMPLISHMENTS

1. Project

- Name: Trends in Austin Crime Data by Zip Code
- **Description:** The city of Austin provides lots of interesting local data sets. We interested in crime data. Base on the data, zip code was the best geographic measure, but also wanted to use demographic data from the Census. We tried to describe each zip code base on four socio-economic indicators: income level, educational attainment, poverty level, unemployment rate. [Team Project]

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/GROUP-PROJECT-Trends-in-Austin-crime-data-by-zip-code

Prezi Link: https://prezi.com/view/46V1XovwTPcJulr4D0rN/ (for project presentation)

2. Project

- Name: Machine Learning Real Estate Project (The Relationship between Stock Market & Real Estate Price)
- **Description:** The purpose of this project was to build a real-estate pricing model with a dataset which we gathered from Real Estate Investment Trust (REIT). In this project 8 popular machine learning models were used, such as Decision Tree Regression, Random Forest Regression, K Nearest Neighbors Regression, Support Vector Machine, Ridge Regression, XGBoost, Lasso Regression, Baseline Model. [Team Project] **Link:** https://github.com/fmsayin/Machine-Learning-Real-Estate-Project

3. Project

- Name: European Soccer League Analysis (Euro League)
- **Description:** European Soccer League vs GDP data set was analyzed. The success of teams has positive correlation with the GDP of its country. Each teams scorers and goals data were analyzed. The results were compared with the country and city's GDP. [Team Project]

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/ETL-Project-EuroLeague

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

DATA ANALYST

Cosmos Trading Inc., Austin, Texas, USA / January 2019 - Present

- Used advanced Microsoft Excel to create pivot tables and pivot reporting as well as VLOOKUP function
- Optimized data collection procedures and generated reports on a monthly and quarterly basis to provide objective advice to the executive board to make the correct decisions
- Successfully interpreted data in order to draw conclusions for managerial action and strategy

Most Recent Project

- **Project Name:** Stock Market Analysis between 2018 2019
- **Description**: Analyzing data from particular stock market movements. Used pandas to get stock market information for visualization. The tools used: python, pandas, numpy, matplotlib, seaborn, beautiful soup for web scraping, and some statistical analysis of the stocks.

DATA ANALYTICS & VISUALIZATION

The University of Texas at Austin, Texas, USA / October 2018 – April 2019 Completed Projects

- 1. Gaming Data Analysis | Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Heroes_of_Pymoli
- 2. The World Cities Weather vs Latitude | Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Weather Py
- 3. Rental Movie Database | Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/mysql challange
- 4. Web Application for Weather Analysis | Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Web-Visualization.github.io
- 5. The Most Successful Start-Up Projects Data Analysis | Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/advanced_excel
- 6. New York City Bike Analytics with Tableau | **Link**: https://github.com/fmsayin/New-York-City-Bike-Analytics-with-Tableau

DATA & RESEARCH ANALYST

Freelance, Austin, Texas, USA / August 2016 - September 2018

- Researched to publish a scientific article in several international journals.
- Completed some social projects as a freelance researcher and analyst.

Completed Project

- Project Name: Effects of unsuccessful coup attempt happened on July 15th, 2016 in Turkey
- **Description**: After the military coup attempt, 4 million individuals were affected (500 650 individuals were arrested, 2285 educational Institutions, 1600 NGOs, 189 media outlets and 15 universities were shut down). Each institution and occupational group data were analyzed.
- Tools: Python, pandas, numpy, matplotlib, seaborn, beautiful soup for web scraping.

DATA & RESEARCH ANALYST

Basari University Research Center, Samsun, TURKEY / September 2014 - July 2016

- Optimized data collection procedures and generated reports on a monthly and quarterly basis to provide
 objective advice to the university executive board to make the correct decisions.
- Used advanced Microsoft Excel to create pivot tables and pivot reporting as well as VLOOKUP function
- Successfully interpreted data in order to draw conclusions for managerial action and strategy
- Used statistical techniques for hypothesis testing to validate data and interpretations
- Analyzed academic evaluations to report to the university senate and set reasonable, achievable academic
 goals.
- Wrote academic research, made informed recommendations, managed the planning and development of design and procedures of metrics reports for short and long terms.